Hi everyone,
I'm so excited to be here with you all, presenting my talk,
uhm, titled Me, Myself, and Claude.
How I leverage AI-assisted development to scale my R-based data
science consultancy. I'm Jasmin.
But a little bit more about who I am.
I'm an R developer and data scientist since about 2014.
I'm the maintainer of four R packages,
ShinyLP, ttbBeer,
AviListR, and ShinyFat,
and we'll go over the last two, uh,
in the upcoming slides as well.
I'm the Principal Consultant at Daily Analytics.
Focused on delivering solutions with data science,
analytics, AI. Focused on non-profit and mission-driven orgs.
Uhm. Advantage both the technical and the writing aspect of
the consultancy, as well as the sales and marketing aspect.
And just to also level set everybody,
uhm, I am also the mom of two young kids with really good resources.
Uhm, I'm an active volunteer in my community.
So, uh, leveraging AIS's development in my practice has been a
real game changer and I'm so excited to preview some of my thoughts and
concepts and how I like- Let's Umm,
aisis development and specifically cloud and cloud code.
So I came upon- on this post and this image on LinkedIn and it
was a really great description of a lot of thoughts I think that have
been flying around in my head. Umm,
really around moving beyond vibe coding.
Umm, vibe coding is this funny little term that's popped up.
Uhm, but it's really important that we understand that having
the proper language helps us to orient the conversation.
Around the work that we're actually doing,
besides some of the fun silly stuff or the mistakes that we're highlighting.
Web coding often implies reckless,
hopeless, hope-based development rattler.
Umm, vibe engineering is intense.
Intentional can be a countable, uhm,
AI system development. Umm,
and what I like to phrase, uh,
about How I'm doing is using a lot more words and not just using,
uhh, the small little phrases.
I'm using a new, agentic tool,
I'm adding a new agentic tool to my toolbox.
And it's an honest acknowledgement about exploration phase of,
like, this hyperb- growth mode and learning,
uhm, and it really helps reframe and understand and not devalue the
work that I do and the work that I've done. Before AI,
um, has come into place. Um,
and so I really like, um, for us to,
as we're going forward and think as- you're just seeing the rest of the
sides, like, this is all, umm,
a new tool in our toolbox, a new way of thinking.
Umm, it's not reckless, it's not hope-based.
There's a lot of deep intention in what I'm building.
For my clients. So,
part one, strategic thinking unlocked for greater community contributions.
questions. So,
the mental bandwidth shift of where I was at,
probably around this time last year before I was- using AI and my
code development and my practice. Umm,
as the principal consultant and developer,
I spent in- enormous amount of time writing code.
Umm, totally what I signed up for,
brings me a lot of joy. Umm,
but really- We doesn't allow me to spend the really meaningful time
doing business development, networking,
uhh, the community. The aspect and the real,
sometimes the real joyful aspects of this work.
And what I found, looking back from- All right.
So, thank Thank you. All right. Last year to now, with AI, integrated into
my development process, I get to steal a little bit of that time back.
back. And partition it across more emphasis on business development
and business operations, which is really important for scaling and growth.
Um And as well as getting back into the community and our stats
community, which really brings me a lot of joy and really helps connect up
the wall. Why? Of what I do, uhm,
and giving back. And so, it's been a really interesting shift about,
uhm, having the same amount of time and- limited at that,
um, and where it goes towards and what I can now do,
now that I leverage, AI-assisted code development.
So,
what that really buys you, to kind of flesh it out,
uh, better be- is ops. Uhm,
I get to spend a lot of time improving my systems,
automating things, standardizing things,
uhh, coming f- from being a,
um, a developer to now being a business owner.
Uhm, efficiency is key where I spend my time.
It is really important, um, and it's important to have systems that match up,
uhm, the way I think and the way I want to operate this business.
And it really, it's a sustainable,
thoughtful way that doesn't also lead to burnout.
Uh, having a lot of understand,
time to understand, cash flow. Pricing strategy,
profitability, packaging, uhm,
the services up that I do, it really opened up a lot more time
to think about. Uh,
these aspects, uh,
relationship building, uh, I've been able to go to so many more in-person events,
virtual events, like this one. On creating content and posts and community engagement,
um, and it's been so wonderful to get back out there,
um, and meet more people. And hear about what they're doing and the ways
in which they're solving their problems. So,
the creative space, uh, really the w- room to think about what could be
built and not just what must be built.
It's a really fun time I'm finding,
uhm, to be- We'll you in the not just super heads down in what
I'm doing, uhm, but really think about,
well, if I had more time, if I had,
uh, you know, a couple more hours,
what could I build? Umm, that could be interesting,
that could be fun, that could be silly, that could change,
have somebody else- umm, goes about their work,
umm, and so that's been really exciting to have that creative space back.
So, uh, going to- you o-go overview,
uhh, a package that I wrote, uhh,
called Shanei Fa, uhh, and I was released,
uhh, a little earlier. 3 3 4 last, uhh,
the shear. Umm, and so really starting at the client problem.
Umm, so I had a client,
and it took me a very, very long time to onboard,
umm, to their application. Umm,
grateful for their patience and their guidance. Umm,
but it was massive. ... Stream massive, shiny-up.
Lots of different files, interconnected functions uh,
the structure of it.
Challenging it almost. Sometimes not fun to work on it.
Sometimes you get a, you know, a shot to your confidence when you're kind
of fighting file systems and folders and,
uh, just not where you want to be.
Um, and so I thought Hey, like,
I'm writing shiny and great, but also I can leverage some of my other
skills in R. Why don't I apply that to the overall on boarding and
getting to understand what I'm looking at.
And so that worked into a quick little script,
kind of, what-off functions Umm,
where the output, right, on the right-hand side is the file name,
and the type, and the name, and having just this level of information
in this format, umm,
was game changer, umm,
really helped. Thank you. To connect up what I was doing,
what changes I was making, how I needed to understand different parts of the
code. Umm, and so then that led to the thought process of the
outs that I've had before, if it's helping me now,
could it help somebody else? And so I turned it into a package,
which is published on CRAN, um, and I really hope all y'all can test
drive it and let me know if it also helps.
And prove your development aspect when it comes to navigating large training applications.
And so, yes, before AI, It's a nice,
some day project, but with AI,
I built this and released it in weeks.
weeks. The next package,
uh, that I developed recently this year,
um, it's called Avi Listar, uh,
and not super technical lifts,
uh. Uh, being really forthcoming about that.
Um, I have this new hobby this year,
birding. Uh, it's fun, it's relaxing,
being in nature. If you're enjoying and being around birds.
And so, I found this newly released taxonomy.
me. Uh, sheet in Excel. Uhm,
and it's great, right? Excel, we can all work with Excel for the most
part. Uhm, but I want to- to have this opportunity to think,
well, can I make an R package?
That's silly. Like, an R package with burn it.
Umm, that is not a,
you know, a large technical lift, but maybe it could be more accessible for
folks. Umm, and so it's a really large,
Excel sheet, um, wrapped it up,
um, and has always really interesting aspects,
uh, about this, I built this in a weekend,
uh, for me personally,
uh, I,
I was never moving at this speed,
uhm, for a contact setting.
The two previous packages I published,
Shane, A. L. P. and T. T. B. Beer,
were published in 2016.
Avi Lister, uh, which was published in June on Cray,
This year, that is eight years and nine months between
my first set of our packages. Could you hear this?
And this new set. Umm,
I feel this sense of hyper-productivity,
excitements, umm, and just- Just have a good day.
Having the aspect of integrating AI in this development
for packages and community-based tools to be- really transformative,
um, and I know there's a lot of aspects of things that were going
on within the last eight years and nine months but I really want to-
to underscore what I've been able to do,
um, just this year,
um, in giving back to the community and thinking grander.
you're up. about, um, how do I contribute open source code?
And so, yes. Right.
It's not even a. Very crucial package,
in my opinion. But it is nice to have.
It is fun. Um, and it has now really lovely,
And a lot of really great examples about
how you integrate this data with some of the existing,
uhh, packages. Like, re-bird, umm,
and so this is my little, umm, my little passion project and my gift
to the art community. community.
So, uh, really holding on,
like, AI system development is the creative multiplier,
umm. 3 4 and it doesn't save me time on what I was already
doing. It, it doesn't away. But it really unlocks what
I wasn't able to do. Uh,
what I wasn't able to complete, what I wasn't able to prioritize,
uh, simply because when you are having,
uh, Bye. I'm running a solo consultancy,
um, and being really strategic about your time and protecting your mental health.
Um, very often, sometimes you don't get to do- the really fun things.
Um, and so now that I've been able to leverage it in my work
processes, able to automate all those- biz dev and biz op systems,
it was right much better unit tests and documentation and package branding and hex
stickers. Shout out to Chet t makes- I find it really wonderful,
uhm, to collaborate on making those really engaging hex stickers.
Umm, and then just having more time.
And then for community engagement and knowledge sharing and networking.
Uh, that for me is a really important aspect of the work
I do. And how I show up. And I'm so glad to have been,
um, leveraging AISIS development and cloud code in my process.
process. Because I feel like it's not just me,
which is great right now. It is everybody.
It is all of our learning path. It is all of our creative endeavor
and to be able to, one, provide this for my clients,
then also provide it for our community, which I love so much.
Umm, has felt really, really meaningful.
Alright, saying yes to bigger and funnier problems.
So, uh,
this is a aspect of,
um, how I think about work.
work. Um, whether I am working for myself,
for me, my consultancy, or I am,
um, you know, doing- other types of volunteer work,
um, or other types of work in the community.
And so, it really sits around the client work- uh,
working with values-aligned clients,
um, while working with non-profits and misin-driven organizations.
Um, these are- that are doing really important boots-on-the-ground,
highly interpersonal work in this world.
And I love being able to be in service- to them.
I also really love, um,
opportunities to grow technically, um,
work on problems that I may not- have the full answer for,
but I have an excitement around it. Umm,
exploring new approaches. Umm, and this work keeps things interesting.
Nexting. Umm, and,
uh, mentally engaging. Umm,
another aspect is community,
uh, professional development. I love- going to networking events,
umm, I love going to conferences,
umm, and it's really important for me.
Um in that aspect. And as well as intentional rest,
umm, all of this does not work unless that- That's it.
I have a really good sense of when is work
and when is family and friends.
friends. time because all of this is in service for that true goal.
And for me, when all of those things hit,
uh, that is. I'm not going for me professional joy.
And that is what I optimize for in my consulting practice.
Um, and it really drives me.
. Umm, in the decisions I make, and the folks that I interact with.
So, my old filter before ASIS development was coming to a potential
new project or a prospect or a client, can I build this in a
reasonable time frame with my current skill sets?
Giving my existing client workload.
That's- that's what I told myself. Now,
with leveraging cloud and cloud code- and agentic development,
my first thought is, I can certainly build it.
But, how can I thoughtfully- Please.
I spend time deeply understanding the desired outcome,
the client restraints, and the overall delivery.
Uhm. So,
I just clawed really as my coding partner,
and sort of the mental model around it, is.
With that, I'm the manager. I set direction.
I make the architectural decisions. Uh,
clawed is my senior. Sometimes my junior developer,
Depending on the context that you give it, um,
a partner in that endeavor. Implementing solutions,
handling boilerplate code, uh,
starting out any of the,
um, scaffolding for packages or shiny applications.
Um, and. Alright.
Alright, now, couple of really seeing cloud code as my coding partner means that
I am both, like, the human in the process and on- on.
So, in and on the loop,
active technical leadership stays with me.
I'm both integrated at various different- intersections in the entire process.
And that is a,
uh, table stakes for me. And so- So ways in which I
help manage this partnership, uh,
must be really specific with requirements and roles for Claude.
Uhm, I always review the generated code.
Uh, Claude has this wonderful way of you can,
you can, when you set up your context files,
you can. Have it just, uh,
writing code and committing to your GitHub repository and not being a part
of that discussion. And that conversation,
that work pattern form, um,
for me, I always need to be in the next for that reviewing code.
Um, and to say that, I always use really incremental commits.
Um, I love how Claude can,
uh, write really detailed- Inhale. Commit messages.
I love being able to possibly unwind things back and forth,
and so that's super important for me. And feeding it- documentation links have been
really helpful to help, uh,
keep Claude focused and giving it accurate information.
and you next time. I'm also asking for multiple options.
I find really using Claude, in addition to coding,
as a brainstorming partner, uh,
to get me started. On a lot of,
uh, the work that I do. And then,
I love to run Claude, sometimes, depending on the project.
I can,
Amplify my impact to take on bigger and more interesting problems.
So, a client example that I really love,
um, is I- needed to set up a data orchestration repo,
uhm, with a lot of understanding about the client's requirements.
They're technical. I call skill capabilities.
Um. GitHub actions made a lot of sense,
and so working in API.
Nice and webhooks, and mixing in real way,
uh, for a VM, um,
learning more about how to structure this Yeah,
I'm. Um, but learning,
learning from clog, right? Uh,
loading the data in the seaweed base, having a real hand on the wheel,
I would say. In terms of the road level,
um, and client isolation aspect for the data security and governance aspect.
Umm, and then having all of those client dashboards be written in quarto,
and this client really needed to be able to scale a repeatable,
ehm, ETL process,
uh, secure data layers,
um, in a database,
um, for persistency. See? And having the dashboards have the ability,
um, to scale and pull each throw data.
Uh, well, also having a sh- shared components and template system where
client could feature toggle on and off different aspects of the dashboard.
forward. And so this is a really interesting system I was able to develop,
uh, primarily with Claude Code,
um, a lot of back and forth.
Uh, it's a lot of understanding about what the requirements were for this project.
Um, and a lot of learning on my part,
um, about- how to write better GitHub actions and how to,
um, have, uh, GitHub actions do PRs in other repositories.
stories. And have a whole lot of process going,
uhh, so this is a really, really fun example,
a and really about.
Building right-sized enterprise-grade infrastructure,
um, in just a few weeks with CloudKit's help.
And this would not have been possible before.
So, my usual client project workflow is understanding the requirements,
defining the problem, the technical approach. generating some of the implementation,
cloud writes the initial code, uh,
review and course correcting, uh, reviewing every line,
checking for issues. Umm, and iterating based on that feedback,
fixing problems, refining the solution, uh,
and that also then the final QA.
I'm sorry. I deliver a testing thoroughly and then shipping to the client.
Um, it's used human decisions at the start,
the middle and end, and AI executions sprinkled in the- middle.
So I am ruthlessly solutions focused at this moment,
thanks to Cloudcode. Um,
it's made me- be even more a better partner,
umm, for my clients, I believe.
I'm not thinking about STACs, I get to think about their outcomes.
I'm not thinking about debugging YAML for GitHub Actions.
I get to solve business problems alongside,
um, the stakeholders.
My mental energy goes to what matters,
uh, and understanding client needs and delivering that value.
Thank Thank you. I love still matter.
I'm still very entrenched in writing code nearly every day.
Uh, but they don't consume my cognitive l- load anymore.
Um, I am not just a person on the computer.
I get to communicate and talk and have these really important And uh,
interpersonal relationships with my clients.
So, uh, building up your intuition in R.
Or, Or, through volume. So I like to think of all of the
learning that I've been doing, umm,
as, ah, high ways, right?
Traditional learning, umm, a smaller focused highway,
a few hours, you get to see a few different I appreciate it as
you ring the deck. Recommendation, you're learning,
you're checking stack overflow. Umm,
it can be really, kind of, slow.
Meaningfully slow, sometimes, but, I like to think of AI-assisted
learning when it comes to involving it in agentic development,
is, seeing many approaches in very
short amount of time. Umm, and being really mindful of a lot more- More.
Through put, uh, through that highway system,
you have to be mindful some things are gonna go awry,
and you need to be able to distill.
Uh, what is the core aspect of what you're directly needing,
and, uh, what is just wrong,
loosening. And so,
I'm gonna go
over. Umm,
one package mistake. a couple,
a couple of mistakes that happen even in the development.
I'll be right back of this talk, which I used, um,
Cloud Code to help me build out all of these slides.
Um, Cloud just doesn't read the docs sometime.
and I'm like, just like you as a human,
like if you're rushing and you're not reading, you're going to make mistakes because
you haven't read about how to do it right.
Um, and so I had Claude,
do a little bit of structure around the- any first slides.
And it just pretended that this package meant something around using font-awesome
icons, right? Thank you. Or see, like,
how it potentially got there, like, the F.A.
from, um, font-awesome,
like, sure. Um, and- then the real error,
like, it didn't even install the package,
and, like, a guest, uhm,
about the vignettes and examples, and you would think,
uh, having access to, uhm,
the package, locally, because I built it,
on my machine, would help give it some different context.
But it enabled the,
uhm, the LLM to, uh,
learn, but it really hadn't.
Um, so even- sometimes packages really establish packages with way more examples out
there, uhm, for, uh,
LLM to pull from. you uh, g-plot too.
Sometimes it just confuses a lot of functions as well.
Um, and why this happens,
right? You can be experienced. is and busy and assume some things come easy
and so you circumvent the system of learning.
Um, and so sometimes this forces you to actually Actually,
we, the document to actually feed claw the documentation URL so it can help
self correct for that. Um,
and I think this make sure you better at evaluating.
And knowing where good docs live.
So, uh, mistake number two, uh, that happened right when I- I was building
the slides for this talk. Um, data structure assumptions.
Um, Claude likes to assume and fur,
um, from- column names and some state of types if they're not at all,
um, matched up or cleaned well and the relationship.
Um, but sometimes that is just wrong.
Umm, I was building the slide for Obulistar and
it wanted to say that, uh,
for that. to drag the bar chart, uh,
the data set was called AviList Global, um,
which doesn't exist. It's AviList 2025.
Um, and. It assumed also,
uh, some examples from the column names that were lower case or snake
case when actually the column. one. More so matches the,
umm, the original Excel file.
And so, umm. Mm. This kind of example where it infers
the connection instead of, like, asking for maybe a look-up table or having access
to actual art. Umm,
and this happens because, like, experience oftentimes breeds assumption and use verification,
and you just assume, like, wha all, this is sometimes common place,
right, to your snake place versus, title case.
And so lesson is, like, Thank you very much. Often, like,
please, like, very, please leverage,
like, MCP tools, um, to give quad actual access to our session
in the context. Um, if those packages are loaded,
if those, uh, those objects are stored there,
um, and,
Let uh, NCP tools like integrate and breed the environment that you're in.
And this mistake, I think, from a human aspect,
teaches you, about proper data inspection habits.
Um, skills which you should be using constantly,
I think, in our world as data practitioners.
Cheers. Umm, but often, like, Claude is making these very similar mistakes.
Umm, and it's really interesting to see it shown.
Uhh, mistake- 3 over abstraction.
This is probably my biggest gripe with Claude.
Umm, it always reaches for the complex solution first.
It's always- Always. It's trying to be overly clever. And this example that was-
I had when building this slide deck is it tried to do this really-
Really. Integrate, integrate,
uh, intricate, uh, sinky diagram,
um, and it just started making up functions.
Um, It just, it created some nested functions,
when like, a simple, like, dplyard chain would work.
Um, and- We're up.
Often, you- I think it's sometimes the examples that it's pulling from
to make its decision about, um,
what it's providing you- . . . . and in like, sometimes people are
trying to show their expertise. They're trying to build the proper systems.
They're trying to, sometimes, that leads to over-engineering.
Um. And when really you're kind of missing out on the focus of like,
um, simple is often better.
Um, and then I like to ask Claude a very deep personal,
uhm, interaction with me like, why?
Doing it this way, uhm, very often because I've spent so much time without
AI. I do know the solution,
I do know the path forward, I do know the exact packages that I
want not called to use and leverage,
and I asked it why it's doing it, and I feed it,
um, some different options, um,
and I try and select the way that is simplest,
the way that I would actually And so recognizing
on my sorry complexity has been really helpful to guiding.
I did. In the partnership with cloud code in my,
uh, telemetry. And so,
um, right. Here's some tips for.
your skills. Building better prompts from these mistakes,
uh, feed documentation links upfront,
uh, data assumptions, use MCP tools.
Give them, look at, look up tables,
um, if columns are coded in other ways,
um, over extraction,
ask for- We're going to multiple approaches, request sometimes the simplest solution to start.
Uh, learning at scale, like,
you're going to encounter these patterns so much more- or,
uhm, rather than the traditional learning.
Um, and each failure, I think, helps refine your prompting skills and your R-intuitive-
so that you don't make those mistakes,
and so you can help clone, make those mistakes less.
And I think it makes you not- on. I think you become a better
technical leader, and you know how to redirect when things go wrong,
and leverage what you're- learning from Claude to bring to the real world as
you're interacting with folks, uhm,
to create better software.
for. So, I really like to think of this all as,
like, the, the skill development,
um, and so the art of the practice is See ya.
It's not necessarily about the final product alone. It's the process.
Awesome. It's just about getting there,
uh, understanding patterns,
learning from mistakes, building that intuition up.
Umm, high-value iteration and failing fast
in course correcting, and deliberate practice and pattern recognition.
mission. And the personal satisfaction and growth
from overcoming those challenges.
Jeez. And maintaining motivation and staying disciplined.
I really think ASIS development accelerates this practice by increasing But the
discipline of learning is still your own.
So, in conclusion, um. Yum.
I really want everybody to really hopefully take away,
um, this thought pattern of learning for your
s- self, and then also writing down your values when it comes to
interacting with AI, uhm, in your work,
in your- for fun, uhm,
and before your next AS is to project,
like, please go through this exercise, write it down.
What will I all- What I do myself.
What AI can help me with.
What I need to understand deeply.
And what I'm comfortable delegating.
So, some final thoughts. Uhm,
I believe. Uh. Ha! When AI frees up your mental bandwidth,
you don't get lazy. You get strategic.
Always building with intention. Thank you. Staying curious about those failures.
Staying strategic about solutions.
And staying joyful in the work because if we're- not all having fun doing
this, I don't think any of this is worth it.
So please always remember, have fun,
have joy. Umm. Take that intentional rest,
be really mindful about what you're building, who you're building it for,
uhm, and ensure that you're not causing any more harm,
uh. Through your actions and,
uh, your software that you're making. Thank you so much.
I've had such a- I'm happy to take questions
after. You can reach me if I'm in most places at- at Jeff.
Uh, Stu Moss, you can, uh, visit my website,
dailynalix.com. Um,
and yes, thank you so much. Bye.
Bye.